In the last video, we talked
在上一段视频中，我们讨论到（字幕翻译：中国海洋大学，郭帅）
about the recommender system problem,
关于推荐系统的问题
where for example, you may
例如，你可能
have a set of movies and you
有一些电影并且你
may have a set of users,
还可能有一些用户
each of whom has rated
每个用户评价了
some subset of the movies,
其中的一部分电影
rated the movies 1 to
评价电影1星到
5 stars or 0 to 5
5星或者从0星到5星
stars, and what I would like
我想要
to do, is look at
做的是，去看看
these users and predict how
这些用户并且预测
they would have rated other movies that they have not yet rated.
他们是怎样评价那些他们还没有评价的电影的
In this video, I would like
在这段视频中，我想
to talk about our first approach
讲一下我们的第一个方法
to building a recommender system, this
来建立推荐系统
approach is called content based recommendations.
这个方法被叫做基于内容的推荐
Here's our data set from before,
这是我们之前的一个数据集
and just to remind you of a
仅仅是为了让你回想起
bit of notation, I was using
一些符号，我使用
Nu to denote the number
nu 来表示用户数量
of users, and so that's equal
这里它的值是4
to 4, and Nm
用nm
to denote the number of movies, I have five movies.
来表示电影的数量，我有5部电影
So, how do I predict
所以，我要怎样预测
what these missing values would be?
这些缺失的值是多少？
Let's suppose that for each
我们假设对于每一部
of these movies, I have a
电影，我有一个
set of features for them.
它们的特征集
In particular, lets say that
尤其是，我们规定
for each of the movies I have two features,
对于每一个电影都有两个特征
which I'm going to denote X1 and
这里用x1和x2表示
X2, where X1 measures the degree
其中x1衡量
to which a movie is a
一部电影为爱情片的程度
romantic movie and X2 measures
用x2来衡量
the degree to which a movie is an action movie.
一部电影为动作片的程度
So if you take a movie
所以如果选了love at last这部电影
Love at last, you know,
可以看出
0.9 rating on the
0.9程度
romance scale, it is a
在爱情片范围内，这是一部
highly romantic movie but zero on
纯爱情片，在动作片范围内的程度是0
the action scale, so almost no
所以几乎没有
action in that
动作成分在这个
movie. Romance forever was 1.0,
电影里。电影Romance forever程度是1.0
lot of romance and 0.01 action,
有很多爱情成分并且动作成分只有0.01
I don't know maybe
我不知道可能
there's a minor car crash in
有一起小型车祸
that movie or something, so little bit of action.
在这部电影里或者是别的，动作成分太少了。
Skipping one let's do
跳过一个我们
Swords vs,. karate, maybe that
来看swords vs karate这部电影，或许
has a zero romance rating
它的爱情片程度为0
and no romance at all in that
没有一点爱情成分
but plenty of action and you know, non-stop car chases.
但是有大量动作成分，不停的上演飞车追逐
Maybe again there is
或许这部电影里有
tiny bit of romance in
一点点爱情成分
that movie, but mainly action,
但是主要的是动作成分
and and Cute puppies of
电影cute puppies of love
love again but mainly a romance
又是一部爱情片，
movie with no action at all.
没有动作成分
So if we have features
所以如果我们有
like these then each movie
一些像这样的特征，那么每部电影
can be represented with a feature vector.
可以用一个特征向量来表示
Let's take movie 1, so just
比如说第一个电影，
call these movies you know, movies 1 2, 3, 4 and 5.
我们将这5部电影叫做电影1，2,3,4,5
For my first movie,
对于电影1
Love at last, I have
love at last，我有
my two features, 0.9 and
两个特征，0.9和
0, and so these are features
0，这两个特征
X1 and X2, and
就是x1和x2的值
let's add an extra feature
我们加一个额外的特征
as usual, which is my
像往常一样，
interceptor feature X0, which is equal to 1
用x0来标示，它的值是1
and so, putting these together,
把这些放在一起
I would then have a feature X1,
然后我有一个特征x1
the superscript 1 denotes it's
上标是1标示
the feature vector for my first
它是电影1的特征向量
movie, and this feature
这个特征
vector is equal to one.
向量等于1
The first one there is this interceptor,
第一个元素值为x0,值是1
and then my two features 0.9, 0,
然后是我的两个特征0.9 和0
like so.
就像这样
So, for Love at last, I
对于电影1
would have a feature vector X1,
我们有一个特征向量x1
for the movie Romance Forever, we
对于电影2
have the separate feature vector
我们有一个特征向量
X2 and so on, and
x2 并且
for Swords vs. karate I would
对于电影5
have a different feature vector x superscript 5.
我们有一个不同的特征向量x5
Also, consistent with our
并且与
early notation that we were
我们之前用的符号一致
using, we're going to set N
我们用集合n
to be the number of features, not
来表示特征数量，
counting this X zero
不包括x0这个特征
intercept term so n is
所以n
equal to two because we have
等于2，因为我们有
two features x1 and x2
特征x1和x2
capturing the degree of romance
来表示每部电影里的爱情程度
and the degree of action in each
和动作程度
movie.
Now in order
现在为了
to make predictions, here is one thing we could do,
作出预测，我们可以这么做
which is that we could treat predicting
我们把预测
the ratings of each user
每个用户的评价看做
as a separate linear regression problem. So
一个线性回归问题
specifically lets say that for each
特别是对于每一个
user j we are going
用户j我们
to learn a parameter vector theta
用一个参数向量theta j,
J which would be in R3 in this case,
这里是三维的
more generally theta j would
通常theta j
be in r n+1, where
在n+1维中
n is the number of features,
n是特征数量
not counting the intercept term, and we're going
不算特征x0， 我们
to predict user J as
预测用户j
rating movie I, with just
评价电影1，
the inner product between the parameters
就是参数向量
vector theta and the features "XI".
theta和特征x1的内积
So, let's take a specific example.
举一个特殊的例子
Let's take user one.
对于用户1
So that would be Alice and
就是Alice
associated with Alice would
和Alice有关的
be some parameter vector,
是一些参数向量
theta 1 and our
theta 1 并且
second user Bob will be
第二个用户Bob
associated, with a different
和一个不同的
parameter vector theta 2.
参数向量theta相关
Carol will be associated with a
Carol将会
different parameter vector theta
和theta 3参数向量相关
3 and Dave a different
Dave 将会
parameter vector, theta 4. So
和theta 4相关
lets say we want to make a
我们想要做一个
prediction for what Alice will
关于Alice将会
think of the movie, Cute
如何评价电影3的预测
puppies of love. Well that
那么
movie is going to have some
电影3有一些
parameter vector X3, where
参数向量x3
we have that X3 is going
我们让它
to be equal to 1
等于1
which is my intercept term, and
也就是特征x0
then 0.99, and then 0.
然后是0.99和0
And let's say for this
对于这个例子
example, let's say that you
我们假设
know we have somehow already gotten
我们已经得到Alice的
a parameter vector theta 1
参数向量theta1
for Alice--we we will
我们
say later exactly how
过会会详细说明
we come up with this parameter
我们是怎么得到这个参数向量的
vector--but let's
但是
just say for now that you
我们说目前
know some unspecified learning algorithm
你知道一些未指明的学习算法
has learned the parameter vector
已经学习了参数向量
theta 1 and it is
theta1并且它
equal to 0 5 0. And so
等于[0 5 0]
our prediction for this
我们对于它的预测
entry is going to
将会
be equal to theta 1,
等于theta1
that is Alice's parameter vector,
这就是Alice的参数向量
transpose X3, that
将x3转置
is the feature vector for
这就是对
the Cute Puppies of Love movie number 3.
电影3的特征向量
And so the inner
并且
product between these two vectors
这两个向量的内积
is going to be 5 x 0.99.
是5*0.99
Which is equal to 4.95.
其值为4.95
And so my prediction for value this
那么这里我们的预测值
over here is going to be 4.95.
就是4.95
And maybe that seems like a
或许它看起来像
reasonable value, if indeed
一个合理值，如果
this is my parameter vector theta 1.
这是我们的参数向量theta1
So all we doing here is
这里我们所做的是
we are applying a different copy of
我们使用一个不同的
essentially linear regression for each
线性回归的副本对于每一个用户而言
user and we are saying
并且我们说
that what Alice does, is
Alice所做的
Alice has seem some parameter vector
是她将参数向量
theta 1 that she uses,
theta1
that we use to predict
我们用来预测
her ratings as a
她的评价，看做是
function of how romantic and how
电影中爱情成分和动作成分怎样组成
action packed the movie is
的一个功能
and Bob, and Carol, and
并且bob，Carol,
Dave each of them have a
Dave 他们每一个都有
different linear function of the
一个不同的线性方程
romantic-ness and action-ness or the degree
来标示爱情成分和动作成分
of romance and the degree of action
的程度
in a movie,
在电影中
and that that is how we're going to predict their star ratings.
这就是我们怎样预测出他们的评价的
More formally here is
这里更正式的是
how we can write down the problem.
我们怎样能写下问题
Our notation is that RIJ
我们将Rij记为1
is equal to one, if
user J has rated movie I,
如果用户j评价了电影i
and YIJ is the rating
Yij是对那个电影的评价
of that movie if that rating exists.
如果评价存在的话
That is if that user has actually
如果用户真的
rated that movie. And
对那个电影进行评价，并且
on the previous slide we also
在之前的ppt我们也
defined theta J which
定义了theta j
is a parameter for each user XI
是每个用户Xi的一个参数
which is a feature vector for specific
Xi是对于特定电影的特征向量
movie and for each user
对每一个用户
and each movie you would predict
和每一个电影，你会像下面这样预测
that rating, as follows.
So let me introduce,
下面我将引入
just temporarily, introduce one extra
仅仅是暂时的，引入一个额外的
bit of notation mj, we
标记Mj,我们
are gonna use mj to denote the
用Mj来表示
number of users rated by movie
评价了电影j的用户数量
j, we're gonna need this
我们需要这个
notation only for this slide. Now, in order to learn
标记，仅仅是为了这个ppt，现在，为了
the parameter vector for
thetaj的参数向量
theta j, well, how can we do so?
我们该怎么做?
This is basically a linear regression problem.
这是一个基本的线性回归问题
So what we can do, is
我们可以
just choose a parameter vector, theta j,
选择一个参数向量，theta j
so the predicted value
这里的预测值
here are as close
尽可能接近
as possible to the values
那些
that we observed in our training set, the values we observed in our data.
我们在训练集中观察的值
So, let's write that down.
让我们将这些写下
In order to learn the
为了学习
parameter vector theta j, let's minimize over
参数向量thetaj，让我们缩小
my parameter vector theta j,
参数向量thetaj，
of sum--
and I want to sum
我想将
over all movies that user
所有用户评价的电影求和
j has rated--so we write this as sum
所以我们这样写
over all values of i
所有的i值求和
that is a colon rij equals 1.
r（i，j）等于1
So the way to read this summation index is
我们可以这样来看索引
this is summation over all
这是所有i值得总和
the values of i, so that
这样来，
r i j is equal to 1.
Rij等于1
So this is going to be summing over all the
所以这样就是对
movies that user j has rated.
所有用户j评价的电影求和
And then I am going to
然后我将要
compute theta j
计算theta j
transpose xi so
Xi转置
that's the prediction of user
这就是
j's rating on movie i,
用户j对电影i的评价
minus y i j,
减去Yij
so that's the actual observed rating squared,
这是实际观测评价的平方
and then, let me just divide
然后我们
by the number of movies
除以
that user J, has
用户j
actually rated, so just divide by 1 over 2MJ.
真实评价的电影数量，
And so this is
这就
just like the least squares regression,
像最小平方回归
it's just like linear regression
就像线性回归
where we want to choose
我们选择
the parameter vector theta J, to minimize this type of squared error term.
参数向量thetaj,来缩小这种方差
And if you want to, you can
并且如果你想，你可以
also add in a regularization term
加入一个正则相
so plus lambda over 2m, and
lambda+2m
this is really 2MJ because,
这就是2Mj
this as if we have MJ examples right?
因为这就好像我们有Mj样本
Because if user J has
因为如果用户j
rated that many movies, it's
评价了许多电影
sort of like we have that many data points with which to fit
这就好像我们有许多数据点来
the parameters theta J. And then
对应参数thetaj,并且
let me add in my usual
我加入
regularization term here of
正则项
theta J K squared.
theta J K的平方
As usual this sum is from
通常这个和是k
K equals 1 through N
从1到n
so here theta J is
这里theta j
going to be an N plus
是一个n+1
1 dimensional vector where,
维的向量
in our early example, n was equal to two,
在我们以前的例子里，n等于2
but more generally, n is
但是通常情况下，n是
the number of features we have per movie.
每个电影所拥有的特征数量
And so as usual we don't regularize over theta 0.
并且我们不会调整theta0
We don't regularize over the
我们不会调整
biased term because the sum is
偏差因为和是
from K1 through N. If
从k1到kn
you minimize this as
如果你将
a function of theta J you get a
theta j这个公式最小化，你会得到
good solution, you get a
一个好的解决方案，你会得到
pretty good estimate of a parameter vector theta j
一个很好的对参数向量theta j的估计
with which to make the predictions
用来对
for user J's movie ratings.
用户j的电影评价做预测
For recommender systems, we're going
对于推荐系统，我们将
to change this notation a little
这个符号稍微改变一下
bit. So to simplify the subsequent math,
为了简化后来的数学公式
I'm actually going to get rid of this term MJ.
我将去掉Mj
So that's just a constant right
这就是一个常数
so I can delete it without changing
所以我能删除他而不用改变
the value of theta J that
thetaj的值
I get out of this optimization,
我从最优化中得到的
so if you imagine taking this
所以如果你想象用这个
whole equation, taking this
公式，用这个
whole expression and multiplying it by
表达并且用
MJ and get rid of that constant, and when
Mj乘以它，并去掉那个常数，
I minimize this I should still get
当我最小化这个，我应该得到
the same value of theta J as before.
和之前一样的数值
So, just to repeat what
为了重复
we wrote on the previous slide, here
在之前ppt写下的东西
is our optimization objective: In order
这里我们最优目标：
to learn theta J, which is
为了学习thetaj
a parameter for user J,
用户j的一个参数
we're going to minimize over theta j
我们将最小化thetaj
this optimization objectives. So
这个最优目标
this is our usual squared
这是方差
error term and then this is our regularization term.
这是我们的正则项
Now of course in building
当然在构建
a recommender system we don't
推荐系统过程中我们不仅是
just want to learn parameters
想要学习
for a single user, we want
单一用户的参数，我们想
to learn parameters for all of
学习所有
our users, I have n subscript u
用户的参数，我用nu
users, so I want to
用户，我想
learn all of these parameters and
学习所有这些参数
so what I'm going to do
并且我将要
is take this minimization, take
用这个最小化，
this optimization objective and just add an extra summation there.
用这个最优目标并且加入一个额外的和
So, you know, this expression here
这个表达式
with the one half on top again, so
..................................
it's exactly the same
这完全和
as what we have on top except
上面得到的是一样的，除了
that now, instead of just
与其
doing this for a specific user theta
仅仅为了特定用户theta做这个
J, I'm going to sum
还不如我对
my objective over all of
所有用户的目标求和
my users and then minimize
并且最小化
this overall optimization objective.
这个最优目标
Minimize this overall cost function.
最小化这个方程
And when I minimize this
当我最小化这个theta1-theta nu
as a function of theta 1,
的方程
theta 2, up to
theta NU, I will
我将
get a separate parameter
得到
vector each user and
每个用户的参数方程
I can then use that
然后我就能用这个
to make predictions for all of
来对所有
my users for all of
nu个用户进行预测
my N subscript u users.
So putting everything together, this
总体来讲
was our optimization objective on
这就是我们的最优化目标
top and to give
为了
this thing a name, I'll just call this
给他起个名字，我就叫他
J of theta 1,
theta1,theta2...theta nu 的j
dot, dot, dot theta NU.
So J as usual is my
j是我
optimization objective which I'm trying to minimize.
试图最小化的最优化目标
Next, in order to actually
下面，为了
do the minimization, if you
实现最小化，如果你
were to derive the gradient
用梯度下降发
descent updates, these are
the equations you would get,
你会得到这些方程
so you would take theta
用theta jk
JK and subtract from
减去alpha
it alpha, which is the learning rate, times these terms here on the right.
alpha是一个学习速率，在右边乘以这些项
So we have slightly different cases
我们得到不同的例子
so when K equals 0 and when K is not
当k等于0时，k不等于0时
equal to 0, because our regularization
以为我们的正则项
term here regularizes only the
仅仅对
values of theta JK for
thetajk的值进行调整
K not equal to zero. So
这里k不等于0
we don't regularize theta 0
部门不调整theta 0
so the slightly different updates
对于k的变化等于0
for k equals zero, and k not equal to 0.
k不等于0
And this term, over
这一项
here, for example is just a partial
仅仅是
derivative with respect to your parameter,
对于你的参数的偏导数
that of your
是你的
optimization objective, right?
最优目标，对不？
And so, this is just
这是
gradient descent and I've
梯度下降
already computed the derivatives and plugged them into here.
我们已经计算出导数并将其放到这
If these gradient
如果这些
descent updates look a
梯度下降变化
lot like what we had for
很像我们
linear regression, that's because these
在线性回归中得到的，这是因为
are essentially the same as linear regression.
这些本质上和线性回归是一样的
The only minor difference is that
唯一不同之处在于
for linear regression we have
对于线性回归，我们
these 1 over M terms
有1到m项
- it's really 1
它实际上是
over MJ - but
1到Mj
because earlier when we were
但是因为以前当我们
deriving the optimization objective
求最优目标时
we got rid of this, that's why we don't have this 1 over M term.
我们去掉了这个，这就是为什么我们没有1到m项
But otherwise it's really sum over
但是它是
my training examples of, you
误差训练集合的和
know, the error times
乘以
XK plus that regularization
Xk加上正则项
term contributes to the derivative.
得到偏导
So if you are using
所以如果你用
gradient descent, here is how
梯度下降法
you can minimize the cost
这就是怎样最小化方程j
function j, to learn all
为了学习所有
the parameters, and using these
的参数，我们用
formulas for the derivatives, if
这些求偏导的公式
you want, you can also plug them
如果你想，你可以同样
into a more advanced optimization
用一个更先进的最优化方法
algorithm like cluster gradient or
比如像群集梯度或者
LBFGS or what have you, and use
LBFGS或者你有的其他方法，并且用
that to try to minimize the cost function J as well.
这些方法来最小化方程j
So hopefully you now know
现在你知道
how you can apply essentially a
怎样使用一个
variation on linear regression in
线性回归的变化来
order to predict different movie ratings by different users.
预测不同用户对不同电影的评价
This particular algorithm is called
这个特殊的算法叫做
a content based recommendations, or
基于内容的推荐算法
content based approach because we
因为我们
assume that we have available
假设我们有
to us, features for the different movies.
可以使用的不同电影的特征
So we have features that
我们用这些特征
capture what is the
来表示
content of these movies. How romantic is this movie?
这些电影的内容，这个电影有多浪漫
How much action is in this movie?
这个电影里的动作成分有多少
And we are really using features of the
并且我们使用这些特征
content of the movies to make our predictions.
来进行预测
But for many movies we
但是对于许多电影都是
don't actually have such features,
没有这样特征的
or it may be very difficult to get
或者很难获取
such features for all of
所有电影的此类特征的
our movies, for all
对于
of whatever items we are trying to sell.
我们正试图出售的所有的任何项目。
So in the next video, we'll
所以在下一段视频中
start to talk about an approach
我们将开始讲解一种
to recommender systems that isn't
不是基于内容的推荐系统方法
content based and does not
并且不假设
assume that we have
我们拥有
someone else giving us all of these features,
别人给我们的所有这些特征，
for all of the movies in our data set.
在我们的数据集所有的电影。